<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief and plain exposition of the creed, commonly called the Apostles Creed. By Christopher Cartwright minister in York.</title>
            <author>Cartwright, Christopher, 1602-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74654</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C683</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1421_1*</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209463</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868345</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868345</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169937</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74654)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169937)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 182:E1421[1*])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief and plain exposition of the creed, commonly called the Apostles Creed. By Christopher Cartwright minister in York.</title>
                  <author>Cartwright, Christopher, 1602-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>115, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by T. Broad,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at York :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: An exposition of the creed.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apostles' Creed --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169937:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A brief and plain EXPOSITION of the CREED, commonly called The Apoſtles Creed.</p>
            <p>By Chriſtopher Cartwright Miniſter in York.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 Iohn 10. 11.</bibl>
               <p>If there come any unto you, and bring not this Doctrine, receive him not into your houſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bid him God ſpeed. For he that biddeth him God ſpeed, is partaker of his evill Deeds.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at York by <hi>T. Broad.</hi> 1649.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169937:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169937:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:169937:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:169937:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>IT is required of Chriſtians, that (according to their places and Callings) they <hi>contend earneſtly for the faith once delivered to the Saints, Iud. v.</hi> 3. &amp; ſurely there is great need to contend for it now, when ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doe contend againſt it; when ſcarce any thing in religion is ſo fundamentall, but ſome impugne &amp; oppoſe it. But how ſhall they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the faith, and not rather be drawn away from it, who are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quite ignorant of it, or not well and throughly grounded in it? Such as are <hi>children</hi> [<hi>in underſtanding,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 20.] are apt to be <hi>toſſed to and fro, and carryed about with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:169937:4"/> 
               <hi>winde of doctrine, by the ſleight of men, and cunning craftineſſe, whereby they lie in wait to deceive, Epheſ.</hi> 4. 14. They are eaſily <hi>led captive,</hi> who are <hi>ever learning, but never able to come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 6, 7. Therefore, as in the exerciſe of my Miniſterie, to prevent (as much as in me lay) the ſpreading of errour, I have handled <hi>the firſt principles of the Oracles of God,</hi> as they are called, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5. 12. ſo in reference to that end, I think this compendious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Creed, (wherein thoſe firſt Principles are compriſed) may be uſefull and profitable unto many. It is called <hi>Creed</hi> of the firſt word wherewith it begins in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, <hi>viz. Credo,</hi> which is in Engliſh <hi>I beleeve;</hi> or becauſe thoſe things which every one ought <hi>credere,</hi> that <hi>it to beleeve,</hi> are contained in it. It
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169937:4"/> is likewiſe called <hi>The Apoſtles Creed,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ruffinus in Symb.</note> and ſome conceive that it was fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Apoſtles, each of them (before they departed one from another to preach in ſeverall places of the world) contributing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing towards the compoſing and perfecting of it. But though this be an ancient, yet (ſo farre as I can ſee) it is an uncertain Tradition. It ſufficeth us, that (as is evident by comparing it and the Writings of the Apoſtles together) it containeth in it ſummarily the Faith, which was once delivered by the Apoſtles. In the explicating of it I have ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyed to be brief, yet ſo as not to be obſcure, but to joyn together per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuity and brevity, as much as might be, that by the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Expoſition all might be encouraged to peruſe it; and by the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169937:5"/> plainneſſe of it all might enjoy ſo much benefit as in a competent meaſure to underſtand what they profeſſe, and ought to beleeve. I will uſe no further preamble, but praying that thou mayeſt by it, and all other good means attaine to a more clear apprehenſion of, and a more firme eſtabliſhment in the truth, I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord, <hi>Ch. Cartwright.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Febr. 28. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="exposition">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:169937:5"/>
            <head>A brief and plain Expoſition of the Creed, commonly called the Apoſtles Creed.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>I beleeve in God, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Why it is ſaid, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve.</note> I <hi>Beleeve</hi>] Faith which is belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that is the doctrine of faith, (which is ſometimes called faith) is the ſame in all that beleeve a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right. <hi>There is one faith,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul, Epheſ.</hi> 4. 5. And of this faith ſpeaks S. <hi>Jude</hi> when he exhorts <hi>to contend earneſtly for the faith once delivered to the Saints, Jude v.</hi> 3. But faith where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we beleeve, (which is faith pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called) that is, the grace of faith, is diſtinct in each Beleever.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169937:6"/> All true Beleevers beleeve the ſame things, yet each one with a diſtinct faith, wherewith himſelf is indued. <hi>The juſt ſhall live by his faith, Heb.</hi> 2. 4. that is, by his own faith, not by the faith of another; therefore is it here ſaid, <hi>I beleeve,</hi> and not <hi>We beleeve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What it is to beleeve in God.</note> 
               <hi>In God</hi>] There are three acts of faith, as it is converſant about God, as the object of it. 1. To beleeve that there is a God; <hi>He that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to God, muſt beleeve that God is, Heb.</hi> 11. 6. 2. To beleeve God, that is, to aſſent unto that which God doth ſay, and to be perſwaded of the truth of it; <hi>I beleeve God, that it ſhall be even as it was told me,</hi> ſaid <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 27. 25. 3. To beleeve in God, that is, to truſt in him, and to relie on him as our God. <hi>O my God, I truſt in thee, Pſal.</hi> 25. 2. <hi>Let him truſt in the Name of the Lord, and ſtay upon his</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:169937:6"/> 
               <hi>God, Iſa.</hi> 50. 10. The two former acts of faith may be exerciſed about men, but not this laſt act. We may beleeve that ſuch or ſuch a man is, and that what he ſaith is true; but we may not beleeve, that is, truſt in him. <hi>Put not your truſt in Princes, nor in the ſonne of man, &amp;c.</hi> that is, in no meer man whatſoever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146. 3. <hi>Curſed is he that putteth his truſt in man, &amp;c. Jer.</hi> 17. 5. The two firſt acts of faith, as exerciſed about God, are common to the wicked, and to the very devils; but this laſt act is peculiar to the godly. The Devils beleeve that God is, and that his Word is true. <hi>The Devils alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve and tremble,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>James, Jam.</hi> 2. 19. But onely the righteous doe beleeve in God, onely they truſt in him, and relie on him, as their God; this neither the Devils, nor wicked men can do.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:169937:7"/>
            <p>They tremble to think of God, and with <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve, Gen.</hi> 3. would runne away, and hide themſelves from God, if they could. Indeed for a while hypocrites and ungodly perſons may profeſſe faith and affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in God, they may ſeem to truſt in him, and to relie on him; as it is ſaid of ſuch, <hi>Mic.</hi> 3. 11. <hi>Yet will they lean upon the Lord.</hi> But when their Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences are thorowly awakened, and they are made ſenſible of the condition they are in, then is that fulfilled, <note place="margin">Iſai. 33. 14.</note> 
               <hi>The ſinners in Sion are afraid, fearfulnes hath ſurpriſed the hypocrites; Who among us ſhall dwell with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring fire? who among us ſhall dwell with everlaſting burnings?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">That there is a God, &amp; but one God.</note> 
               <hi>In God</hi>] As there is a God, which the very light of nature doth ſhew; <hi>The heavens declare the glory of God, and the firmament ſheweth his handie worke,</hi> Pſal. 19. 1. <hi>The inviſible things</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:169937:7"/> 
               <hi>of God from the Creation of the world are clearly ſeen, being underſtood by the things that are made, even his eternall power and Godhead, Rom.</hi> 1. 20. ſo there is but one God. Idols are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led gods, becauſe of that opinion which Idolaters have of them. Thus <hi>Jacob</hi> called <hi>Labans</hi> Idols his gods, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31. 32. Judges and Magiſtrates are called gods, becauſe in reſpect of that Power and Authority that they are in, they in a ſpeciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner reſemble God, and are as his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties and Vicegerents. <hi>I have ſaid, ye are gods, Pſa.</hi> 82. 6. <hi>Thou ſhalt not revile the gods, Exod.</hi> 22. 28. But truly and properly ſo called there is but one God. <hi>I am God, and there is none elſe, Iſa.</hi> 45. 22. <hi>Thou ſhalt have none other gods before me, Exod.</hi> 20. 3. <hi>We know that an Idol is nothing in the world,</hi> (that is, no ſuch thing as an
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169937:8"/> Idolater takes it to be) <hi>and that there is none other God but one. For though there be that are called gods, &amp;c. yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us there is but one God, &amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 4, 5, 6. <note place="margin">That God is a Spirit, infinite &amp; eternall.</note> God truly and properly ſo called, is a Spirit, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. 24. And not onely a Spirit, (for ſo the ſouls of men, and Angels alſo are ſpirits, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12. 23. &amp; 1. 14.) but he is an immenſe and infinite Spirit, which none elſe is. <hi>Do not I the Lord fill hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, Ier.</hi> 23. 24. <hi>Yea, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, even the heaven of heavens cannot contain him,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8. 27. God alſo is an eternall Spirit, which neither the ſoul of man, nor an Angel is. <hi>He is the high and lofty one that inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth eternity, Iſa.</hi> 57. 15.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The name of Father how attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted unto God.</note> 
               <hi>The Father</hi>] Sometimes the name of Father being attributed unto God, is taken eſſentially, and is common to the whole Trinitie.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169937:8"/> 
               <hi>Have we not all one Father? hath not one God created us,</hi> Mal. 2. 10. <hi>I will be a Father unto you, and you ſhall be my ſonnes and daughters, ſaith the Lord Almighty,</hi> 2 Cor. 6. 18. Sometimes it is taken perſonally, and belongs onely to the firſt Perſon of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, who is called the Father in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the ſecond Perſon called the Sonne: <hi>Our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 3. Thus is the word <hi>Father</hi> here taken, as appears by that which follows, <hi>And in Ieſus Chriſt his onely Sonne, &amp;c.</hi> The whole Trinity is our Father, but onely the firſt perſon of the Trinitie is Chriſts Father.</p>
            <p>When it is here ſaid, <hi>I beleeve in God the Father,</hi> it is not meant that the firſt Perſon onely, the Father, is God, as if the Sonne were not God, and the Holy Ghoſt God alſo;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169937:9"/>
               <note place="margin">The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther how the firſt Perſon of the Trinity</note> but onely the Father is firſt mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as being the firſt Perſon of the three; the firſt Perſon, I ſay, not in time, nor in dignity (for they are all co-eternall and co-equall) but in order and proceeding. For the Father is of himſelf, not proceeding from any other; but the Sonn pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt both from the Father and from the Sonne. <hi>I proceeded forth and came from God,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 42. <hi>The Spirit of truth which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the Father, Iohn</hi> 15. 26. And ſo the Spirit alſo proceedeth from the Sonne, and is therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the Spirit of the Sonne, Galath.</hi> 4. 6. and is ſaid to be ſent by the Sonne; <hi>Whom I will ſend,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Spirit, or, Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15. 26. which argues that the Holy Ghoſt doth proceed from the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169937:9"/> Sonne, hath the Divine Nature communicated unto him by the Sonne, as well as by the Father, even as the Sonne is ſaid to be ſent by the Father, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 16. and in other places, becauſe hee doth proceed from the Father, and hath the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature communicated to him by the Father. But the Father is never ſaid to be ſent either by the Sonne, or by the Holy Ghoſt, as not proceeding either from the one, or fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other. Thus then the Father is God, and ſo is the Son, and ſo the Holy Ghoſt, all one and the ſame God, though ſeverall and diſtinct Perſons. <hi>Theſe three are one,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 7. They are three, and yet one; three Perſons, yet one God. As Perſons they differ each from other, as God they are the ſame one with another. This is a great Myſterie, which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169937:10"/> though we cannot comprehend, as being above reaſon, yet we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, as being revealed in the Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">As the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, ſo is the Son and the Holy Ghoſt alſo.</note> 
               <hi>Almighty</hi>] This attribute <hi>Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> is not peculiar to the firſt Perſon the Father, but is common to all the three Perſons. As the Father is Almighty, ſo is the Sonne, and ſo the Holy Ghoſt alſo. For God as God, is Almighty, and therefore each Perſon of the Trinitie being God, is Almighty: Yet (as <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> ſaith) there are not three Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighties, but one Almighty. For the Father, the Sonne and the Holy Ghoſt are one and the ſame God, and ſo one and the ſame Almighty.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">That God is Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and how he is Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</note> Now that God is Almighty is clear by Scripture. <hi>I am God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 1. <hi>God Almighty bleſſe thee,</hi> ſaid <hi>Iſaac</hi> to <hi>Iacob, Gen.</hi> 28. 3.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169937:10"/> God is ſtiled <hi>The Almighty. Ruth</hi> 1. 20. 21. <hi>The Almighty hath dealt very bitterly with me,</hi> ſaid <hi>Naomi:</hi> And again, <hi>The Almighty hath teſtified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.</hi> God is Almighty, in that he can do all things whatſoever he pleaſeth. <hi>With God nothing ſhall bee unpoſſible, Luke</hi> 1. 37. True it is, <hi>God cannot lie, Tit.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>He cannot deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 13. But this doth not derogate from his Almightineſſe, becauſe theſe things, to lie, to deny himſelf, and the like, note imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; and to doe them argues weakneſſe, and not Power. <hi>How weak is thine heart, ſaith the Lord, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou doſt all theſe things? Ezek.</hi> 16. 30. God being Almightie, 1, Let us fear to offend him. <hi>Do we provoke the Lord to jealouſie? are we ſtronger then he?</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 10. 22. <hi>Who ever hardened himſelf againſt him, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered?</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:169937:11"/> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> 9. 4. 2. Let us with boldneſſe flie unto him, and truſt in him. <hi>O Lord God of our Fathers</hi> (ſaid <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi>) <hi>Art not thou God in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and ruleſt not thou over all the kingdoms of the heathen? and in thine hand is there not power and might, ſo that none is able to withſtand thee?</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. 6. And verſe 12. <hi>O our God, wilt thou not judge them? for wee have no might againſt this great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany that commeth againſt us; neither know we what to do, but our eyes are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee.</hi> So <hi>Paul, I know</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>whom I have beleeved, and that he is able to keep that which I have committed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him againſt that day,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 12.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How God made hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven earth</note> 
               <hi>Maker of heaven and earth</hi>] Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of heaven and earth. <hi>In the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning God created the heaven and the earth, Gen.</hi> 1. 1. To create is as much as to make of nothing, &amp; ſo God made
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169937:11"/> heaven and earth. <hi>By faith we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that the world was framed by the Word of God,</hi> (the Word of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, his moſt powerfull Will &amp; Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) <hi>ſo that things which are ſeen, were not made of things which do appeare, Heb.</hi> 11. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What is meant by heaven and earth.</note> 
               <hi>Heaven and Earth</hi>] Theſe two being the principall parts of the world, are put for the whole world, and all things in it. Sometimes the Sea (being a vaſt body) is alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. <hi>The God of heaven, which hath made the Sea, and the drie Land, Ionah</hi> 1. 9. Sometimes heaven, earth and Sea, and all that is in them; as <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi> 9. 6. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 12.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Heaven how taken.</note> By <hi>Heaven</hi> is meant, firſt, The Air, which in Scripture is called Heaven. <hi>The fowls of heaven,</hi> that is, of the Air, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79. 2. and ſo in other places. Secondly, that higher Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169937:12"/> wherein are the Sunne, Moon, and Starres, which are therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The hoſt of heaven, Deuteron.</hi> 4. 19. And thirdly, above theſe Heavens there is <hi>a third Heaven,</hi> as it is called 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 12. 2. which is the place of Bliſſe and happineſſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is called <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 4. This ſeems to be it alſo which is called <hi>The Heaven of Heavens,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8. 27. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 9. 6. That is, the higheſt and moſt excellent heaven; as Song of Songs, that is, a moſt rare and excellent Song.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To be the Maker of Heaven &amp; Earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, as to the Father, ſo alſo to the Sonne, and to the H. Ghoſt.</note> Now as the Attribute <hi>Almighty</hi> belongs to all the three Perſons, ſo alſo doth this, <hi>Maker of Heaven and Earth.</hi> It belongs to the Father; <hi>There is but one God, the Father, of whom are all things,</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 8. 6. yet not to the Father onely, but to the Sonne alſo. <hi>One Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:169937:12"/> 
               <hi>whom are all things,</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 8. 6. <hi>All things were made by him, and without him was nothing made that was made, John</hi> 1. 2. So <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 16. And ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to the holy Ghoſt; <hi>The Spirit of God hath made me,</hi> ſaid <hi>Elihu, Job</hi> 33. 4. And he that made him, made all. As God made all things, ſo in and for all things is he to be glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>The Lord hath made all things for himſelf,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> that is, for his own glory, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. 4. <hi>For of him, and through him, and to him are all things; to him be glory for ever, Amen. Rom.</hi> 11. 36. See <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9. 5, 6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4 10, 11.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">As God made all, ſo he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves and governs all</note> Furthermore, as God is the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, ſo he is alſo the Preſerver, and Governour of all things. In this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect Chriſt ſaid, <hi>My Father worketh hitherto, and I worke, John</hi> 5. 17. On the ſeventh day hee ceaſed from working, ſo as not to Create any
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169937:13"/> more kindes of Creatures, but in reſpect of Preſerving and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Creatures he ceaſed not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth ceaſe. <hi>Thou preſerveſt them all, Nehem.</hi> 9. 6. <hi>His Kingdome ruleth over all, Pſal.</hi> 103. 19. In this reſpect alſo is God to be glorified. <hi>O bleſſe our God people, and make the voice of his praiſe to be heard; which holdeth our ſoul in life, and ſuffereth not our feet to be moved, Pſalm.</hi> 66. 8, 9.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Neceſſary to beleeve in Ieſus Chriſt.</note> 
               <hi>And in Jeſus Chriſt</hi>] As it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to beleeve in God, ſo is it to beleeve in Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Ye beleeve in God, beleeve alſo in me,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt, John</hi> 14. 1. Chriſt is the onely Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator betwixt God and us, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5. We cannot have acceſſe to God, but by Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 14. 6.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What the name Ieſus doth import.</note> 
               <hi>Ieſus</hi>] This name <hi>Jeſus</hi> comes of a word in the Hebrew that ſignifies <hi>to ſave,</hi> and it imports as much as a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169937:13"/> 
               <hi>Saviour. Thou ſhalt call his Name Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, for he ſhall ſave his people from their ſinnes,</hi> ſaid the Angel to <hi>Joſeph, Mat.</hi> 1. 21. where the reaſon of the name is rendred. And the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> had ſaid before unto <hi>Mary, Thou ſhalt conceive in thy Wombe, and bring forth a Sonne, and ſhalt call his Name Jeſus, Luke</hi> 1. 31. To which words (not to the other related by S. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> though that place be noted in the Margent of our Bibles) S. <hi>Luke</hi> hath reference afterward, when he ſaith, <hi>And when eight dayes were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed for the circumciſing of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Childe, his name was called Jeſus, which was ſo named of the Angel before he was conceived in the Wombe, Luke</hi> 2. 21. Chriſt was conceived in the Womb before the Angel ſpake to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout naming him <hi>Ieſus,</hi> but not when he ſpake to <hi>Mary</hi> about it. By
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169937:14"/>
               <note place="margin">Ioſua, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua, and Ieſus, are all one name. Compare Ioſ. 1. 1. &amp; other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with Neh. 8. 17. &amp; Heb. 4. 8</note> the Name <hi>Ieſus</hi> is ſometimes meant <hi>Ioſua,</hi> who after <hi>Moſes</hi> was Captain and Commander over the Iſraelites, and brought them into <hi>Canaan.</hi> See <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 45. and <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4. 8. <hi>Ioſua</hi> in thoſe places is the <hi>Ieſus</hi> that is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of; he had the ſame name with our Saviour, and was a Type and Figure of him. So alſo we read of others who were likewiſe called <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> but all <hi>Ieſuſſes</hi> beſides the Lord <hi>Ieſus</hi> Chriſt, were either onely Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours in name, not in deed; or but temporall and Typicall Saviours; onely our Lord Jeſus is the true and everlaſting Saviour. <hi>Ieſus Chriſt yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever, Hebr.</hi> 13. 8. <hi>He is the Author of eternall ſalvation to all them that obey him, Hebr.</hi> 5. 9. <hi>Neither is there ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in any other, &amp;c. Acts</hi> 4. 12. See <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 11.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:169937:14"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What the name Chriſt ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi>] Our Saviour in the Old Teſtament is called <hi>Meſſiah, Dan.</hi> 9. 25, 26. In the New Teſtament he is called <hi>Chriſt.</hi> The words <hi>Meſſiah</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſignifie both one thing, onely the one is Hebrew, the other Greek. See <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 41. and 4. 25. They ſignifie as much as <hi>Anointed.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 25, 26. with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 1, 2. The reaſon of the Name appears, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. 7. <hi>God hath anointed thee with the oyl of gladneſſe above thy fellows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Chriſts threefold Office.</note> This name <hi>Chriſt</hi> imports the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to which our Saviour was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed, which Office was threefold, <hi>viz.</hi> the Office of a Prieſt, the Office of a Prophet, &amp; the Office of a King. Kings were anointed, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 1. and ſo other places ſhew the ſame. Prieſts alſo were anointed, <hi>Exo.</hi> 29, 7 And <hi>Eliah</hi> is commanded of God,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169937:15"/> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19. 16. to anoint <hi>Eliſha</hi> to be Prophet in his roome; which ſeems to be meant of outward an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointing, as Kings and Prieſts were anointed. But that outward and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible anointing with oyl did ſignifie inward &amp; inviſible anointing with the Spirit, and ſo onely was our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour anointed; not any materiall Oyl, but the Spirit was powred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. See <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 34. &amp; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61. 1. with <hi>Luke</hi> 4. 18. &amp; 21. Chriſt was anointed to be a Prieſt; <hi>Thou art a Prieſt for ever after the Order of Melchiſedec, Pſ.</hi> 110. 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t was ſpoken to our Saviour, as is ſhewed, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5. 6, 10. and 6. 20. and 7. 15, 17, 21. Chriſt was a Prieſt to offer himſelf a Sacrifice unto God for our ſins, and to make atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for us. <hi>He appeared to put away ſinne by the ſacrifice of himſelf, Hebr</hi> 9. 26. Therefore he is called <hi>The Lamb</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:169937:15"/> 
               <hi>of God that taketh away the ſinne of the world, Iohn</hi> 1. 29. And as a Prieſt Chriſt doth ſtill <hi>make interceſſion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God for us, Hebr.</hi> 7. 25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 34. Chriſt was anointed to bee a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. See <hi>Deuter.</hi> 18. 15. with <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 22. and 7. 37. Chriſt came as a Prophet to make known the Will of his Father unto us. <hi>No man hath ſeen God at any time; the onely begotten Son, which is in the boſome of the Father, hee hath declared him,</hi> John 1. 18. <hi>God who at ſundry times, and in divers manners ſpake in times paſt unto the Fathers by the Prophets, hath in theſe laſt dayes ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto us by his Sonne, &amp;c.</hi> Heb. 1. 1, 2. <hi>I know that Meſſias commeth, which is called Chriſt; when he is come, he will teac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us all things,</hi> John 4. 25. And as Chriſt, when hee was upon earth, did teach in his owne perſon, ſo doth hee ſtill by his Miniſters;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169937:16"/> 
               <hi>Teaching them to obſerve all things that I have commanded you; and lo I am with you alway to the end of the World,</hi> Mat. 28. 20. <hi>He that heareth you, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth me; and he that deſpiſeth you, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth me,</hi> Luke 10. 16.</p>
            <p>Chriſt was anointed to be a King. <hi>Zach.</hi> 9. 9. with <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 5. Chriſt as a King doth reign in the hearts of Beleevers, ſo that ſinne doth not reign in them, nor have dominion over them. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 12, 13, 14. and ſee 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 9. and <hi>Philip.</hi> 4. 13. As a King Chriſt doth protect and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thoſe that belong unto him. See <hi>Act.</hi> 18. 9, 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 35, 36, 37. And as a King he doth deſtroy his enemies that ſtand out againſt him, and will not ſubmit unto him. <hi>Thoſe mine enemies that would not ſuffer me to reign over them, bring hither, and ſlay them before me, Luke</hi> 19. 17. <hi>He muſt</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:169937:16"/> 
               <hi>reign untill his enemies be made his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool,</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 15. 25. This ſhall be fully accompliſhed at Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to judgement, which belongs to his Kingly Office: <hi>He ſhall judge the quick and the dead at his appearing, and his Kingdome,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How Chriſt is the Son, the onely Son of God</note> 
               <hi>His onely Sonne</hi>] Every true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever is the Childe of God. <hi>To as many as received him, to them he gave power to bee the Sonnes of God, even to them that beleeved in his name,</hi> John 1. 12. <hi>You are all the Children of God by faith in Chriſt Jeſus, Galath.</hi> 3. 26. But none are ſo the ſonnes of God as Chriſt is. Others are the ſonnes of God onely by adoption. A ſonne by adoption is one that is freely, and of meere grace, and favour made choice of, and taken to be as a ſonne, when as otherwiſe by nature he is not a ſon; <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 24</note> ſee <hi>Exo.</hi> 2. 10. <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 21
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169937:17"/> 
               <hi>God hath predeſtinated us to the adoption of ſonnes through Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c. Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> 1. 5. <hi>God ſent his Sonne,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that we might receive the adoption of ſonns,</hi> Gal. 4. 6. But Chriſt is the Sonne of God by Generation, he is Gods begotten Sonne; <hi>Thou art my Sonne, this day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave I begotten thee, Pſal.</hi> 2. 7. Thus none but Chriſt is the Sonne of God, this dignity is peculiar un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, neither man nor Angel is capable of it. <hi>To which of the Angels ſaid God at any time, Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee,</hi> Heb. 1. 5. Thus then Chriſt is the onely Sonn of God, that is, the onely begotten Sonne, as he is called <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 16. and in other places. Beleevers are in ſome ſenſe begotten of God; <hi>Of his own will begat he us,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iames</hi> 1. 18. but they are onely in a Metaphori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſenſe begotten of God, in reſpect
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169937:17"/> of that renovation, which God by his Spirit doth worke in them; in which reſpect they are ſaid alſo to <hi>be Partakers of the Divine Nature,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4. Whereas Chriſt is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe begotten of God, having the ſame ſubſtance with God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one and the ſame God with the Father: <hi>I and my Father are one,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. 30. <note place="margin">Chriſt one and the ſame God with the Father.</note> that is, one God, though two Perſons. So <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 1. <hi>In the beginning was the VVord,</hi> (that is, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the ſecond Perſon of the Trinity, the Son; ſee 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 7. and <hi>Revel.</hi> 19. 13.) <hi>and the Word was with God,</hi> (to wit the Father) <hi>and the Word was God.</hi> And <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 5. Chriſt is called <hi>God bleſſed for ever.</hi> And 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 20. it is ſaid of him, <hi>This is the true God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How Chriſt is Lord, our Lord.</note> 
               <hi>Our Lord</hi>] <hi>David</hi> was the Lords Anointed, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 21. and ſo was
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169937:18"/> 
               <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 6. and <hi>Cyrus, Eſay</hi> 45. 1. But Jeſus Chriſt is not onely the <hi>Lords Chriſt,</hi> that is, the Lords anointed, as he is called <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 26. But he is alſo the <hi>Lord Chriſt; To you is born this day in the Citie of David, a Saviour, which is Chriſt the Lord, Luke</hi> 2. 11. Chriſt is <hi>the Lord of glory,</hi> that is, a moſt glorious Lord, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſtiles him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 8. He is the onely Lord; <hi>To us there is but one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by whom are all things,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 6.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is our Lord, firſt, as he is God; <hi>For God is the Lord, Pſal.</hi> 118. 27. As God he made all, and ſo is Lord over all. Secondly, hee is our Lord as he is Mediator betwixt God and man. Thus <hi>all Power both in heaven and in earth is given unto him,</hi> Matth. 28. 18. <hi>To this end Chriſt both dyed and roſe, and revived, that be</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:169937:18"/> 
               <hi>might be Lord both of the dead and living, Rom.</hi> 14. 9. Chriſt hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed and purchaſed us with his blood, and in that reſpect is Lord over us; <hi>He dyed for us, that we ſhould not live unto our ſelves, but unto him, &amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 15. Let none therefore think to be ſaved by Chriſt, except they be obedient unto Chriſt; they that will not have him for a Lord &amp; Soveraign, muſt not think to have him for a Jeſus &amp; Savior. Commonly in the Scripture theſe two are joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together, Lord Jeſus, or Lord and Saviour; if he be not our Lord, he will no bee our Jeſus, our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. <hi>He is the Author of eternall ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all that obey him, Heb.</hi> 5. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of Chriſts incarnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> 
               <hi>Who was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, born of the Virgin Mary</hi>] In the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going words is ſhewed Chriſts Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and Godhead, in theſe and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169937:19"/> the reſt that follow is ſhewed his humanity and Manhood: Yea theſe words ſhew the manner of Chriſts Incarnation, and how he aſſumed our nature. <hi>The Word was made fleſh, John</hi> 1. 14. that is, the ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Trinitie, the Sonne, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med humane nature, and was made man. <hi>Chriſt being in the form of God, thought it not robbery to be equall with God; But made himſelf of no reputation, and took upon him the forme of a ſervant, and was made in the likeneſſe of men: Philip.</hi> 2. 6, 7. He was made man, true man, like unto other men, <hi>yet without ſinne, Hebr.</hi> 4. 15. So that one and the ſame Perſon Jeſus Chriſt, is both God and man; being God from all eternity, in due time, he alſo was made man. <hi>When the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time was come, God ſent his Son, made of a woman, Galath.</hi> 4 4. This
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169937:19"/> woman was called <hi>Mary,</hi> which is the ſame name with <hi>Miriam,</hi> as it is written in the Old Teſtament. When ſhe conceived and bare Chriſt, ſhe was a pure Virgin; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a Virgin ſhall conceive and bear a Sonne, and ſhall call his name Immanuel,</hi> that is, being interpreted, God with us: <hi>Iſai.</hi> 7. 14. It was propheſied of Chriſt, who was conceived and Born of a Virgin, <hi>Matth.</hi> 1. 22, 23. It was not by the concurrence of man, but by the Power of the Holy Ghoſt that Chriſt was conceived in the Wombe of his Mother: <hi>That which is conceived in her is of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> ſaid the Angel to <hi>Ioſeph, Mat.</hi> 1. 20. And ſo the Angel told the bleſſed Virgin, <hi>The Holy Ghoſt ſhall come upon thee, and the power of the moſt High ſhall overſhadow thee, &amp;c. Luke</hi> 1. 35. Therefore Chriſt was holy from
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169937:20"/> his very Birth and Conception, all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, free from that originall pollution, which others, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and borne after the ordinary courſe of Nature, draw from <hi>Adam,</hi> and bring into the world with them; as <hi>David</hi> confeſſed of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 5. That therefore <hi>Iob</hi> 254. <hi>How can man be clean that is born of a woman?</hi> that, I ſay, is meant of ſuch as are borne after the uſuall manner, by naturall generation; it extends not unto Chriſt, whoſe birth was extraordinary, and above nature. As the Virgin did corporally conceive &amp; bear <hi>Chriſt</hi> in her womb, ſo muſt we ſpiritually conceive and bear him in our hearts. <hi>My little Children, of whom I travell in birth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, untill Chriſt be formed in you,</hi> ſaid <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Galatians, Gal.</hi> 4. 19. And Chriſt pointing at his Diſciples,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169937:20"/> ſaid, <hi>Behold my mother and my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. For whoſoever ſhall do the will of my Father which is in heaven, the ſame is my brother, and ſiſter, and mother, Matth.</hi> 12. 49, 50.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of Chriſts Paſſion or ſuffering.</note> 
               <hi>Suffered under Pontius Pilate</hi>] Chriſts whole life was a continuall ſuffering; his very Incarnation was a Paſſion. For him who was God bleſſed for ever, to take upon him the nature of man; for him who was Lord of all, to take upon him the forme of a ſervant, this was a great and wonderfull ſuffering. So whiles hee lived hee was never free from ſuffering. Being newly born he was laid in a Manger, there being no room for him in the Inn where he was, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 7. Eight dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Birth he was circumciſed, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 21. Soon after he was perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by <hi>Herod,</hi> and was fain to be
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169937:21"/> carried into <hi>Egypt</hi> to eſcape the danger he was in, <hi>Matth.</hi> 2. 13, 14, 15. Of the reſt of Chriſts life untill hee was about thirty yeares old, <hi>Luke</hi> 3. 23. the Scripture ſpeaks but little, it being not ſo neceſſary for us to know. Yet thus much it tells us plainly of him, that <hi>he was ſubject to Joſeph and Mary, Luke</hi> 2. 51. And it intimates unto us, that Chriſt did exerciſe the Trade that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> his Mothers husband was of. For whereas it is ſaid <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 55. that ſome did ſay of him, <hi>Is not this the Carpenters ſon?</hi> S. <hi>Mark</hi> relates it, <hi>Is not this the Carpenter? Mark</hi> 6. 3. Which implies, that as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> his ſuppoſed Father, was a Carpenter, ſo he alſo (for a while) did follow the ſame Trade. After that he came abroad to ſhew himſelfe to the world, and to execute the Office for
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169937:21"/> which he was ſent, how was he op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Scribes, and Phariſees, and ſuch as could not endure the holineſſe of his Life and Doctrine? Beſides he ſtill lived a mean and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicable kinde of life; <hi>Though he were rich, yet for our ſakes he became poor,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 9. Even ſo poor, that others <hi>did miniſter to him of their ſubſtance, Luke</hi> 8. 3. And whereas <hi>the Foxes have holes, and the Birds of the air have neſts, he had not where to lay his head, Luk.</hi> 9. 58. Thus was <hi>Chriſt</hi> continually ſuffering all his life long; but the things that he ſuffered at the laſt, at, and immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death, were ſuch, and ſo great, that they peculiarly are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his Paſſion, or Suffering. And this is that which is here ſaid, <hi>Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red under Pontius Pilate.</hi> This <hi>Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Pilate</hi> was Governour of <hi>Iudea</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:169937:22"/> under <hi>Tiberius</hi> the Romane Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, to whom the Jews were then ſubject. See <hi>Luke</hi> 3. 1. <hi>Pilate</hi> was the Judge that gave ſentence upon Chriſt, and condemned him, as all the Evangeliſts record. And even forraign Writers, as namely <hi>Joſephus</hi> a Jew, and <hi>Tacitus</hi> a heathen, teſtifie that Chriſt was put to death by <hi>Pontius Pilate.</hi> But the Scripture re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates as more fully what Chriſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered; to wit, how he was buffetted, ſpit upon, reviled, ſcourged, crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Thorns, &amp;c. ſo alſo why he ſuffered, to wit, not for any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence that he had done; no, <hi>Pilate</hi> himſelf (as the Evangeliſts ſhew) did divers times declare him to bee innocent; but for our ſins, which he was to beare, and to ſatisfie for. <hi>He bare our ſins in his body on the tree,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 24. <hi>Him that knew no ſinne,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:169937:22"/> 
               <hi>God made ſinne for us,</hi> 2 Corinth. 5. 21. <hi>Surely he was wounded for our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, he was bruiſed for our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the chaſtiſement of our Peace was upon him, and with his ſtripes we are healed. All we like ſheep went aſtray, turning every one to his owne courſe, and the Lord laid upon him the iniquities of us all, Iſai.</hi> 53. 5, 6.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of Chriſts crucifying.</note> 
               <hi>Was crucified</hi>] Here follows now more particularly after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Chriſt ſuffered. He was <hi>Crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> that is, nailed alive to the Croſſe, and ſo did hang untill hee were dead. So the Hiſtory of the Goſpel ſhews, and hence the Croſſe of Chriſt is ſo much ſpoken of in the Scripture. This kinde of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was not in uſe among the Jewes, untill they came under the power of the Romans, with whom it was frequent. It was a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169937:23"/> both full of pain, and alſo full of ignominie; onely ſuch as were of meaneſt rank, and vileſt Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors were wont to have this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment inflicted on them: <note place="margin">why Chriſt ſuffered on the Croſſe.</note> yet as painfull and ignominious as it was, Chriſt was content to ſuffer it for our ſakes. Yea, it was a curſed kinde of puniſhment, and therefore Chriſt ſubmitted unto it, to free us from the curſe, which by reaſon of our ſinnes was due unto us. <hi>Chriſt</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>hath redeemed us from the curſe of the Law, being made a Curſe for us; for it is written, Curſed is every one that hangeth on a tree, Gal:</hi> 3. 13. And <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 8, he exaggerates Chriſts hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation by this; that <hi>he humbled himſelf, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the Croſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of Chriſts Death.</note> 
               <hi>Dead</hi>] <hi>The Wages of ſinne is death, Rom.</hi> 6. 23 Not onely the firſt death,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169937:23"/> the ſeparation of the ſoul from the bodie, but alſo the ſecond death, the damnation both of ſoul and body; as appears by the oppoſition in the words there immediately follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>But the gift of God is eternall life through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">why Chriſt ſuffered death.</note> Chriſt therefore ſuffered death, to free us from death, from the ſecond death altogether; <hi>Verily, verily,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>if a man keep my ſaying, he ſhall never ſee death;</hi> he meanes, eternall death, <hi>John</hi> 8. 51. So <hi>John</hi> 11. 26. <hi>He that beleeveth in me ſhall never die,</hi> to wit, eternally. And ſo alſo Chriſt by his death hath freed all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in him from the firſt death, as it is a curſe, ſo that the nature of it is changed, it is now to them as no death, but an entrance into life, even life eternall. <hi>The ſting of death is ſinne,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>and the</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:169937:24"/> 
               <hi>ſtrength of ſinne is the law; But thanks be unto God, who giveth us victory through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 56, 57. <hi>To live to me is Chriſt,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and to die is gain, Phil.</hi> 1. 21. And he adds Verſ. 23. that he deſired to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt, which was farre better for him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How the death and paſſion of Chriſt is ſo efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> The death and paſſion of Chriſt is of ſuch vertue and efficacie, as to ſatisfie for our ſinnes, and to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us from that wrath, which by reaſon of our ſinnes is due to us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his death is not the death of a meer man, but of God himſelf, that Perſon that dyed for us, being not onely man, but God alſo. God as God is immortall, and cannot die, but God aſſuming the nature of man, in that nature, as man, did die for us. <hi>God with his owne blood hath purchaſed his Church, Acts</hi> 20. 28. The
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169937:24"/> blood of Chriſt is the blood of God, and therefore it is indeed <hi>precious blood,</hi> as it is called 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 1. 19. It is a price ſufficient to ranſom and redeem all: Therefore what ever thy ſinnes be, yet, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the Jayler, <hi>Beleeve in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt and thou ſhall be ſaved, Act.</hi> 16, 31.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of Chriſts buriall.</note> 
               <hi>And buryed</hi>] Chriſt being dead, was buried, as the Evangeliſts teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie. And he was buried for theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. <note place="margin">Reaſons why Chriſt was buried</note> Firſt, to ſhew that he was tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dead, and not in appearance one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For men uſe not to be buryed till they be dead indeed. And the Scripture notes unto us, that <hi>Pilate</hi> did firſt diligently enquire, whether Chriſt was already dead, and was certified of that before hee would give leave that he ſhould be buryed, <hi>Marke</hi> 15. 44, 45.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that ſo Chriſts riſing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169937:25"/> from the dead might bee the more conſpicuous and manifeſt. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was not onely buryed, but buried in a Sepulchre hewne out of a Rock, and in a new Sepulchre, wherein none before had been bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27. 60. <hi>Iohn</hi> 19. 41. So that it could not be ſaid either that Chriſts Diſciples did undermine the Sepulchre, and ſo get him away; or that it was not he but ſome other that did ariſe. Neither yet could it be pretended, that Chriſt roſe not by his own power, but by the touch of ſome other that had been buryed there before; as we read of one who being laid in the grave of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> as ſoon as he touched the dead bones of the Prophet, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 13. 21.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Chriſts buryall was a further degree of his humiliation, in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169937:25"/> that he condeſcended and ſtooped ſo low, as to be laid in the Grave, the common receptacle of the dead. <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaking of a man that is moſt potent while he liveth, ſhews how low he ſhall be brought when he dyeth; <hi>Who ſhall declare his way to his face? and who ſhall repay him what he hath done? Yet ſhall hee bee brought to the grave, and ſhall remaine in the Tomb. The clods of the valley ſhall be ſweet unto him, Iob</hi> 21. 31, 32, 33.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, this makes Chriſts vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory over death the more glorious, that he not onely dyed, but was alſo buryed; death ſeemed to have full conqueſt over Chriſt, having got him into its Den; yet even there did Chriſt vanquiſh and ſubdue it; <hi>O death I will be thy plagues, O grave I will be thy deſtruction,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13. 14. Now, through Chriſts victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169937:26"/> over death and the grave we may be aſſured that death ſhall bee no plague, the grave no deſtruction to us. We may ſay, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting, O grave where is thy victory?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 55. As Chriſt was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, dead and buryed, ſo alſo muſt we in a Metaphoricall and myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſenſe be crucified, dead and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed; that is, our old man, our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall corrupt nature muſt be crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, dead, and buryed. <hi>They that are Chriſts have crucified the fleſh, with the affections and luſts,</hi> Gal. 5. 24. <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, that our old man is crueified with Chriſt, that the body of ſinne might be deſtroyed, that henceforth we ſhould not ſerve ſinne,</hi> Rom. 6. 6. And v. 3. &amp; 4. <hi>Know ye not that ſo many of us as are baptized into Chriſt, are baptized into his death? Therefore we are buryed with him by Baptiſm into death, &amp;c.</hi> So
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169937:26"/> Col. 2. 12. <hi>Buryed with him by Baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of Chriſts deſcending into Hell, and what is meant by it.</note> 
               <hi>He deſcended into Hell</hi>] As all the other Articles of the Creed are grounded upon, and clear by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo is this alſo: For thoſe words <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 10. <hi>Thou wilt not leave my ſoul in Hell,</hi> ſuppoſe that his ſoul ſhould be in Hell; otherwiſe it were abſurd to ſay, that it ſhould not be left there, if it ſhould never be there: Now that was ſpoken by <hi>David</hi> not of himſelf, but of Chriſt. <hi>For David ſpeaketh concerning him, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter, Act</hi> 2. 25—But what is here meant by <hi>Hell?</hi> Surely not that which we commonly underſtand by the word <hi>Hell,</hi> to wit, the place where after this life the damned are in torment; Chriſt never came there for any thing that we can finde in Scripture, and therefore we have no reaſon to make that any part of our Beliefe.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169937:27"/> The foure Evangeliſts, <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> write of Chriſt from his Incarnation to his Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, yet mention no ſuch thing, as that Chriſt went to Hell in that ſenſe. Neither was it any part of the Goſpell that <hi>Paul</hi> preached, as appears 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 15. 1, 2, 3, 4. There rehearſing ſome of the Heads of the Goſpell which he had preached, he mentioneth Chriſts death, and his buriall, and his reſurrection; but for his going to Hell (the Hell of the Damned) he neither expreſly, nor implicitely makes any mention of it. Again, <hi>David</hi> was left in that Hell, in which Chriſt was not left; This appears by <hi>Peters</hi> argument; which he uſeth to prove that <hi>David</hi> in thoſe words, <hi>Thou wilt not leave my ſoul in Hell,</hi> ſpake in the perſon of Chriſt, and not in his own perſon;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169937:27"/> He proveth it by this, that the words were not true, if meant of <hi>David,</hi> but moſt true as meant of Chriſt: <hi>Men and Brethren,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>let me freely ſpeak unto you of the Patriarch Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, that he is both dead and buryed, and his Sepulchre remaineth with us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day, Acts</hi> 2. 29. By <hi>Davids</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre remaining with them unto that day, he means that <hi>David</hi> was left in Hell, and therefore when he ſaid, <hi>Thou wilt not leave my ſoule in Hell,</hi> did not ſpeak of himſelf, but of Chriſt, and of his reſurrection. <hi>Therefore being a Prophet, and knowing that God had ſworn with an oath to him, that of the fruit of his loyns, according to the fleſh, he would raiſe up Chriſt to ſit on his Throne; he ſeeing this before, ſpake of the reſurrection of Chriſt, that his ſoul was not left in Hell, nor his fleſh did ſee corruption,</hi> Verſe 30. and 31. Now
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169937:28"/> if ſuch a Hell be meant, as in which <hi>David</hi> was left (and ſuch a Hell we muſt underſtand, if we will make S. <hi>Peters</hi> argument good) then can it not be the Hell of the Damned, the place of torment; for <hi>David</hi> was not left in that Hell, he never was in it, being none of the Reprobate, to whom alone that Hell appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Further, it appears rather by Scripture, that when Chriſt dyed, as his body went to the earth, ſo his ſoul went to Heaven; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to Hell, as it ſignifies the place of the Damned. <hi>This day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe,</hi> ſaid Chriſt to the beleeving Thiefe that was crucified with him, <hi>Luke</hi> 23. 43. now by Paradiſe is meant the third Heaven, the place of Bliſſe and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, as appears 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 2. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with 4. Theſe reaſons are
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169937:28"/> ſufficient to evince that by <hi>Hell</hi> here in the Creed, and ſo in thoſe places of Scripture upon which this Article is grounded, is not meant the Hell of the Damned. But, may ſome ſay, what is then meant by it? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, the eſtate of the dead, or the power of death is meant by Hell; and the meaning of the Article is, that Chriſt ſo humbled himſelf, as that for a while he was in the eſtate of the dead, and under the power of death, though (as <hi>David</hi> propheſied of him) he did not long continue in that eſtate, but was ſoon delivered out of it. <hi>Chriſt being riſen from the dead,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>dyeth no more, death hath no more dominion over him, Rom.</hi> 6. 9. That intimates, that for ſome time, though but a ſhort time, Chriſt was under the power of death, and it had dominion over
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169937:29"/> him. This power and dominion of death, whereby it having ſeparated the ſoul from the bodie, keeps it ſtill in that ſtate of ſeparation, untill the body be raiſed up, and the ſoule and it re-united together; this (I ſay) is that which is meant by Hell, when Chriſts deſcending into Hell, or his not being left in Hell is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of. The words in the Originall which are tranſlated <hi>Hell,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sheol. Hades.</note> do not properly and directly ſignifie Hell, as taken for the place of Torment, but they ſignifie either the grave, or the power of death, and the eſtate of the dead in generall, whether their ſouls be in the place of torment, or in the place of comfort. And thus our Engliſh word <hi>Hell</hi> is ſometimes uſed As <hi>Pſa.</hi> 89. 48. in the old vulgar Tranſlation, which is in the Book of Common Prayer, <hi>What man is hee</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:169937:29"/> 
               <hi>that liveth, and ſhall not ſee death? and ſhall he deliver his ſoul from the hand of Hell?</hi> The Interrogation hath the force of a ſtrong Negation, and the meaning is, that certainly there is no man living that ſhall not ſee death; none that ſhal deliver his ſoul fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hand of <hi>Hell,</hi> that is, either of the grave, as our laſt tranſlation hath it, or of the power of death. For it were abſurd there to underſtand the Hell of the Damned, many through Chriſt being delivered from that Hell. And ſo <hi>Revel.</hi> 20. 14. where it is ſaid, <hi>Death and Hell were caſt into the Lake of fire,</hi> by <hi>Hell</hi> cannot be meant the Hell of the Damned, for that is meant by <hi>the Lake of fire;</hi> but the Power and Dominion of death is meant, which after the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there ſpoken of, ſhall have no place any where but in that <hi>Lake of</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:169937:30"/> 
               <hi>fire,</hi> which is there called <hi>The ſecond death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of Chriſts riſing from the dead.</note> 
               <hi>The third day he roſe again from the dead</hi>] After Chriſts humiliation followed his exaltation, the firſt ſtep and degree whereof was his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection or riſing from the dead. That Chriſt roſe from the dead, all the Evangeliſts have diligently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, and the Apoſtles diligently preached. See <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 22. <hi>and</hi> 4, 33. <hi>and</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 4, 15. This Article of Chriſts riſing from the dead, is of ſuch concernment, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, <hi>If Chriſt be not riſen, then is our preaching vaine, and your faith is alſo vain,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15 14. And again, <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>If Chriſt be not riſen, your faith is in vain, you are yet in your ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Reaſons why Chriſt roſe from the dead.</note> It was neceſſary that Chriſt, though hee dyed, and was buryed, and remained a while under the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169937:30"/> power of death, yet ſhould riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. 1. For the fulfilling of the Scriptures. For it was written of him, that his ſoul ſhould not be left in Hell, nor his fleſh ſee corruption, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. 10. Therefore there was a neceſſity of his riſing from the dead, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſheweth, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 24. 25, &amp;c. <hi>Whom God hath raiſed up, having loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the pains of death, becauſe it was not poſſible that he ſhould be holden of it. For David ſpeaketh concerning him, &amp;c.</hi> So elſewhere in the Old Teſtament Chriſt is ſpoken of as abiding for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 4. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 13, 14. Which did not import (as ſome erroniouſly conceived, <hi>John</hi> 12. 32, 33, 34.) that Chriſt ſhould not die, but that hee ſhould not remain dead, but be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up, and live for ever. <hi>O fools, and ſlow of heart to beleeve all that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets have written! Ought not Chriſt to</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:169937:31"/> 
               <hi>ſuffer theſe things, and to enter into his glory? Luke</hi> 24. 25, 26. So ſpake Chriſt to ſome, who ſtartled at his death, and when they were told of his reſurrection, were ſlow to beleeve it. And in that ſame Chapter, <hi>verſe</hi> 45, 46. it is ſaid, that comming to his Apoſtles, <hi>He opened their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they might underſtand the Scriptures. And ſaid unto them, Thus it is written, and thus it behoved Chriſt to ſuffer, and to riſe from the dead the third day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. To make it appear, that by his death he had fully ſatisfied for our ſinnes, and wrought out our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption for us. <hi>Who was delivered for our offences. and was raiſed again for our juſtification,</hi> Rom. 4. 25. <hi>We truſted that it had been he that ſhould have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed Iſrael, Luk.</hi> 24. 21. So they ſpake who knew Chriſt to have been
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169937:31"/> dead, but doubted of his riſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; They did before expect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption by him, but now they had ſmall hope of it. And indeed if Chriſt had onely dyed, and not riſen from the dead, all hope in him might well have dyed with him. But <hi>Bleſſed be God, and the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who according to his abundant mercy hath begotten us againe unto a lively hope through the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Jeſus Chriſt from the dead, unto an inheritance incorruptible and undefiled, and that fadeth not away, reſerved in heaven for us,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 3, 4.</p>
            <p>3. To aſſure us of our reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For the reſurrection of the Members depends upon the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Head; the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſtians depends upon Chriſts Reſurrection. See after up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe words, <hi>The reſurrection of the body.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:169937:32"/>
            <p>
               <label>Queſt.</label> But if Chriſt roſe the third day, to wit, after that he dyed, how is it ſaid, that he ſhould be three dayes, and three nights in the heart of the earth? that is, in the grave, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. 40.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> That is not ſo to be underſtood, as if Chriſt were three dayes and three nights compleat in the grave, but onely ſome part of three dayes, and three nights. He dyed (as the Evangeliſts ſhew) the day before the Jewiſh Sabbath, that is, on Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day (as we call it) in the afternoon, and was buryed the ſame day. That part of the day ſtands for the whole day, and alſo the night going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, which (the Jews beginning their naturall day, that conſiſts of 24 hours, at Evening, <hi>Levit.</hi> 23. 32.) did belong unto it. Then he reſted in the grave all the night following,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169937:32"/> and the next day, which we call Saturday. And the night after hee alſo remained in the grave, riſing early in the Morning on Sunday, as we call it. Now together with that night is rekoned the day following, to which it belonged, and ſo taking the part for the whole (as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is taken) Chriſt was three dayes and three nights in the grave, though otherwiſe hee was little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove two nights and one day in it. After this manner is it ſaid, that <hi>Eſther</hi> and the Jewes did faſt three dayes and three nights, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 4. 16. for the Faſt was ended on the third day, as is clear by <hi>Eſthers</hi> putting on her royall apparell, and addreſſing her ſelfe to the King on that day; <hi>Eſther</hi> 5. 1.</p>
            <p>As Chriſt roſe from the dead cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally, ſo muſt we ſpiritually; wee
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169937:33"/> muſt riſe from the death of ſinne, to the life of grace. <hi>Awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ſtand up from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall give thee light,</hi> Epheſ. 5. 14. <hi>We are buryed with him by Baptiſme in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, that like as Chriſt was raiſed by the glory of the Father, even ſo we alſo ſhould walk in newneſſe of life,</hi> Rom. 6. 4. And Verſ. 11. <hi>Likewiſe reckon ye your ſelves dead indeed unto ſinne, but alive unto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> And <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 12. <hi>Buryed with him by Baptiſme, wherein alſo you are riſen with him, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 1. <hi>If ye then be riſen with Chriſt, ſeeke thoſe things which are above, where Jeſus Chriſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the right hand of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He aſcended into heaven</hi>] This is the ſecond ſtep of Chriſts exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. That Chriſt aſcended into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the Scripture teſtifies, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 19. <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 51. <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 9.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:169937:33"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of Chriſts Aſcenſion into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note> It was requiſite that Chriſt ſhould aſcend into heaven. <note place="margin">Reaſons why Chriſt aſcended into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note> Firſt, becauſe he came down from heaven, not that he brought his body from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, (as ſome Hereticks imagined) but in that by his Incarnation he made himſelf manifeſt upon earth, whereas before he onely kept reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence (as it were) in heaven. <hi>The Word was made fleſh, and dwelt among us, and we beheld his glory, as the glory of the onely begotten Sonne of God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 14. In this reſpect Chriſt is called <hi>The Lord from Heaven,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 47. And its ſaid, that <hi>he came down from Heaven, John</hi> 1. 13. Now as Chriſt thus came down from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſo having finiſhed the worke for which he came, it was meet hee ſhould return to heaven. <hi>I came forth</hi> (ſayes Chriſt) <hi>from the Father, and am come into the world; again, I leave the</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:169937:34"/> 
               <hi>world, and go to the Father, John</hi> 16. 28. And ſpeaking to his Father, <hi>I have glorified thee on earth,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I have finiſhed the work which thou gaveſt me to do. And now, O Father, glorifie me with thine ownſelf, with the glory which I had with thee before the World was, Iohn.</hi> 17. 4, 5.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that it might appeare, that his Kingdome is not of this world, as he ſaid <hi>John</hi> 18. 36.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that hee might ſhew himſelf to triumph over ſinn, death, and him that had the power of death, that is, the Devill. <hi>Thou haſt aſcended on high, thou haſt led captivity captive, Pſal.</hi> 68. 18. That was ſpoken of Chriſt, as the Apoſtle ſheweth, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 8. <hi>To lead captivitie captive,</hi> is as much as to lead a multitude of Captives, as appears by <hi>Iudges</hi> 5. 12.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that he might ſend
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169937:34"/> down the Spirit, and inrich his Church with the gifts and graces of the Spirit. <hi>Thou haſt aſcended on high,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>thou haſt received gifts for men, Pſal.</hi> 68. 18. <hi>When hee aſcended up on high,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>he gave gifts unto men, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ.</hi> 4. 8. <hi>The holy Ghoſt was not yet gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> (to wit in ſuch meaſure as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward) <hi>becauſe that Ieſus was not yet glorified, Iohn</hi> 7. 39. <hi>It is expedient for you that I go away; for if I goe not away, the Comforter will not come unto you; but if I depart, I will ſend him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you,</hi> ſaid Chriſt to his Diſciples, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16. 7.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, that having offered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Sacrifice for us on the Croſſe, he might preſent himſelfe likewiſe unto God in heaven, and make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for us. <hi>For Chriſt is not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the holy places made with hands, which are the figures of the true,</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:169937:35"/> 
               <hi>but into heaven it ſelfe, now to appear in the preſence of God for us, Hebr.</hi> 9. 24.</p>
            <p>6. That he might make way for us to aſcend into heaven alſo. <hi>I go to prepare a place for you,</hi> ſaid he to his Diſciples, <hi>John</hi> 14. 2. <hi>Whither the forerunner is for us entred, even Jeſus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 20. He is called <hi>the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner,</hi> becauſe he going before, and preparing the way, we alſo in due time ſhall follow after. But in the mean time in our hearts and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we muſt aſcend into heaven, whiles in reſpect of our bodies wee are here upon earth. <hi>Set your affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on things above, not on things on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arth, Col.</hi> 3. 2. <hi>For our c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion is in heaven, Phil.</hi> 3. 20.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of Chriſts ſitting at the right hand of God.</note> 
               <hi>And ſitteth on the right hand of God</hi>] This is the higheſt ſtep of Chriſts exaltation. It is expreſly mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 19. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1. 3. and in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169937:35"/> other places. But how is Chriſt ſaid <hi>to ſit?</hi> And how <hi>on the right hand of God?</hi> Firſt, for <hi>ſitting,</hi> it is not here taken properly, as it imports ſuch a diſtinct kinde of bodily poſture. <note place="margin">What is meant by ſitting.</note> It is not the intent of the Holy Ghoſt in the Scripture to ſhew what bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſture now in heaven <hi>Chriſt</hi> uſeth; to what purpoſe were it for us to know that? But <hi>to ſit</hi> (we know) is a poſture of State, and of Authority. Judges and Magiſtrates uſe to ſit, and others in token of reverence &amp; ſubjection, to ſtand before them. <hi>Moſes ſate to judge the people, and the people ſtood by Moſes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Exod.</hi> 18. 14. Therefore to ſhew Chriſts honour and dignity, his power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, he is uſually in Scripture ſaid <hi>to ſit at the right hand of God.</hi> Onely when he appeared to <hi>Stephen,</hi> it is ſaid that <hi>be ſtood at the right hand of</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:169937:36"/> 
               <hi>God, Act.</hi> 7. 55, 56. He then appeared as ready to aid <hi>Stephen</hi> in the great conflict that he endured for his ſake. In this ſenſe God is ſaid to ſit, <hi>God ſitteth upon the Throne of his holineſſe, Pſal.</hi> 47. 8. It notes Gods Majeſtie and Power; for otherwiſe properly God can neither ſit nor ſtand.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What is meant by the right hand of God.</note> So for <hi>the right hand of God,</hi> it is taken metaphorically, and not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly. For <hi>God is a Spirit, John</hi> 4. 24. and therefore properly he hath no hand, either right or left. When eyes, ears, hands, and the like are attributed unto God, it is figurative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Scripture condeſcending to the weakneſſe of our capacity, and ſpeaking of God after the manner of men. Thus here, becauſe amongſt men it is an honour to be ſet at ones right hand, (<hi>Salomon</hi> ſitting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169937:36"/> in his Throne, cauſed his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſit at his right hand, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2. 19.) Therefore Chriſt is ſaid to fit at Gods right hand, to ſhew the high honour to which he is exalted. <hi>The Lord ſaid unto my Lord, ſit thou at my right hand, untill I make thine enemies thy footſtool.</hi> So <hi>David</hi> ſpake of Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 1. The Apoſtle expreſſeth it thus, <hi>He muſt reign untill his enemies be made his footſtool,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 25. So that Chriſts ſitting at the right hand of God, imports his Kingly Power, his reigning over all. It imports that which Chriſt ſaid after his Reſurrection, <hi>All power both in heaven and earth is given unto me, Matth.</hi> 28. 18. <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſt, ſaith, <hi>God ſet him at his owne right hand, Farre above all Principality and Power, and Might, and Dominion, and every Name that is named, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:169937:37"/> 
               <hi>in this world, but alſo in that which is to come, Epheſ.</hi> 1. 20, 21. So S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, that <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riſt is gone into heaven, and is on the right hand of God, Angels, Authorities and Powers being made ſubject unto him,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 22.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt as man ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the right hand of God.</note> Now this moſt high and glorious exaltation of Chriſt, belongs unto him, as man. As in reſpect of his Manhood he ſuffered, was crucified, dead, and buryed, and deſcended into Hell; ſo in reſpect of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alſo hee roſe againe from the dead, aſcended into heaven, and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the right hand of God. So that this ſitting at the right hand of God, doth not import equality with God, for that honour the humane nature is not capable of; but it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports honour next unto God, above all Creatures whatſoever; even as <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns</hi> Mother being ſet at his
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169937:37"/> right hand, and he in his Throne, had honour next to him, above others, yet beneath him.</p>
            <p>This makes wonderfully for the comfort and encouragement of ſuch as truſt in Chriſt, that hee is thus exalted. <hi>Who is he that condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth? it is Chriſt that dyed, yea rather that is riſen again, who is even at the right hand of God, who alſo maketh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for us, Rom.</hi> 8. 34.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of Chriſts comming to judge both the quick and the dead.</note> 
               <hi>From thence he ſhall come to judge both the quick and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e dead</hi>] From whence ſhall he come? Not from the right hand of God, which was immediately before mentioned; no, for then eſpecially ſhall Chriſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to ſit at the right hand of God, when he commeth to judgement; <hi>Hereafter ye ſhall ſee the Sonne of man ſitting on the right hand of Power</hi> (that is, of <hi>God,</hi> to whom belongeth Power
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169937:38"/> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62. 11.) <hi>and comming in the Clouds of Heaven,</hi> to wit, to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. 64. <note place="margin">From whence Chriſt ſhal come to judge the quick and the dead.</note> Therefore theſe words <hi>from thence,</hi> have refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to <hi>Heaven. He aſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heaven, and</hi> (there) <hi>ſitteth on the right hand of God.</hi> And <hi>from thence</hi> (that is, from heaven) <hi>He ſhall come to judge both the quick and the dead.</hi> The Scripture is clear and expreſſe for this: <hi>Ye men of Galilee, why ſtand ye gazing up into Heaven? This ſame Jeſus which is taken up from you into heaven, ſhall ſo come in like manner, as ye have ſeen him go into heaven.</hi> So ſpake an Angel unto thoſe who were with Chriſt at his Aſcenſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 11. So S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to judgement, ſaith, <hi>He ſhall deſcend from heaven,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 16. And 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 7. <hi>He ſhall be revealed from Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:169937:38"/>
            <p>
               <hi>To judge both the quick and the dead</hi>] So likewiſe the Scripture expreſſeth it, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 42. and 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 1. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 5. <note place="margin">Who are meant by the quick and the dead.</note> Now by <hi>quick and dead</hi> are meant, firſt, in generall all, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they be. <hi>We muſt all appeare before the judgement ſeat of Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 14. 10. and 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 5. 10. But more particularly and diſtinctly by <hi>quick</hi> are meant all that ſhall bee found alive at Chriſts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, &amp; by <hi>dead</hi> are meant all that were dead before that time, who then ſhall be raiſed up, and ſo come to judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>I ſhew you a Myſterie, wee ſhall not all ſleep,</hi> (that is, die,) <hi>but we ſhall all be changed; In a moment, in the twinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an eye, at the laſt Trumpe, (for the Trumpet ſhall ſound, and the dead ſhall be raiſed incorruptible, and we</hi> (he means all ſuch as are then found
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:169937:39"/> alive) <hi>ſhall be changed,</hi> 1 Cor. 5. 51, 52. So 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 15, 16, 17. <hi>For this we ſay unto you by the word of the Lord, that we which are alive, and remaine unto the comming of the Lord, ſhall not prevent them which which are aſleepe,</hi> (that is, which are dead) <hi>For the Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaven with a ſhout, with a voice of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angel, and with the Trump of God; and the dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt. Then we which are alive, and remain, ſhall be caught up together with them in the Clouds, to meet the Lord in the aire,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe places ſhew who are meant by <hi>quicke,</hi> who by <hi>dead,</hi> when it is ſaid that <hi>Chriſt ſhall come to judge both the quick and the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Chriſt ſhall bee the Judge of all, beſides the places before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, the Scripture plainly teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 31. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 16.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169937:39"/> which places ſhew, that God will judge all, but by Chriſt, whom he hath exalted, and ſet at his owne right hand, to rule and govern all, and to execute judgement upon all. Thus is that meant <hi>John</hi> 5. 22. <hi>The father judgeth no man, but hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all judgement to the Sonne.</hi> That is, The Father judgeth not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by himſelfe, but mediately by the Sonne, by Chriſt. And the reaſon there follows Verſe 27. <hi>And hath given <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im,</hi> (that is, The Father hath given the Sonne) <hi>Authority to execute judgement alſo, becauſe he is the Sonne of man.</hi> That is, becauſe he is man, and ſo fit to execute judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in an outward and viſible manner. For being man he ſhall be ſeen of men when he commeth to judgement. <hi>Behold he commeth with Clouds, and every eye ſhall ſee him, even</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:169937:40"/> 
               <hi>they that pierced him,</hi> Revel. 1. 7. <hi>Wherefore (beloved) ſeeing you look for ſuch things, be diligent that you may be found of him in peace, without ſpot, and blameleſſe,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt.</note> 
               <hi>I beleeve in the Holy Ghoſt</hi>] After the Articles concerning the two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſons of the Trinitie, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Sonne, followes this Article concerning the third Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the Holy Ghoſt. This Perſon in Scripture is called <hi>The Spirit,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 18. <hi>The Spirit of God;</hi> and <hi>The Spirit of Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 8. 9. <hi>The Holy Spirit,</hi> or, <hi>The</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">The word Ghoſt imports as much as Spirit. Ghoſtly Father, and ghoſtly Counſell, is as much as ſpirituall Father, and ſpirituall Counſell.</note> 
               <hi>Holy Ghoſt, Luke</hi> 11. 13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 5. and 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 7. God as God is a Spirit, <hi>John</hi> 4. 24. And ſo alſo holy, <hi>Iſai</hi> 6. 3. And therefore God the Father is a Holy Spirit, and ſo God the Sonne; yet the name is appropriated to the third Perſon, that Perſon is peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169937:40"/> called <hi>The Spirit,</hi> and <hi>The Holy Spirit,</hi> or <hi>The Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Why the third Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Trinitie is peculiarly called the Spirit, and the Holy Spirit, or the Holy Ghoſt.</note> The third Perſon of the Trinity is peculiarly called <hi>The Spirit,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as being after an ineffable manner breathed forth (as it were) from the Father and the Sonne; or as inſpiring the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>Thoſe holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 21. And this Perſon alſo is peculiarly called <hi>Holy,</hi> as working ſanctification, and making holy. The Father doth ſanctifie, and ſo the Sonne, but by the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>I will put my Spirit within you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zek.</hi> 36. 27. Whence ſanctification is called <hi>ſanctification of the Spirit,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2. 13,</note> becauſe it is wrought by the Spirit. And they that are regenerated, or borne againe, are ſaid to be born of the Spirit, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 5, 6, 8.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:169937:41"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">That the Ghoſt is God.</note> The Holy Ghoſt is God, one and the ſame God with the Father and the Sonne; and therefore as we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in the Father, and in the Son, ſo alſo in the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Theſe three are one,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 7. They are <hi>three,</hi> that is, three Perſons, yet <hi>one,</hi> that is one God. And that the Holy Ghoſt is God, is evident by that <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 3, 4. <hi>Peter ſaid to Ananias, Why hath Satan filled thy heart to lie unto the Holy Ghoſt?—Thou haſt not lyed unto men, but unto God.</hi> And that we are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in the name of the holy Ghoſt, as well as in the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the Sonne, according to Chriſts injunction, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 19. This unanſwerably proves, that as the Father is God, and the Sonne God, ſo is the Holy Ghoſt God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. For we may not be Baptized in the name of any meere Creature.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169937:41"/> 
               <hi>Were ye baptized in the Name of Paul?</hi> ſaid <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">That the holy Ghoſt is a Perſon</note> Again, the Holy Ghoſt is a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, not an Attribute, as Wiſdome, Mercy, Power, and the like; but as the Father is a Perſon, hath proper and peculiar ſubſiſtence, and as the Sonne is a Perſon, ſo is the Holy Ghoſt a Perſon likewiſe. This is clear, as by other places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo by that <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. 16. where it is ſaid that the Holy Ghoſt came downe in the likeneſſe of a Dove. For no meere Attribute, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a Perſon can aſſume a bodily ſhape, wherein to appeare and ſhew it ſelf. Sometimes indeed the Holy Ghoſt is put for the gifts and graces of the Holy Ghoſt. As <hi>Act.</hi> 19. 2. when <hi>Paul</hi> asked ſome, if they had received the Holy Ghoſt, they anſwered, <hi>We have not ſo much</hi>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:169937:42"/> 
               <hi>as heard whether there be any holy Ghoſt,</hi> that is, any ſuch extraordinary gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, which in thoſe Primitive times were beſtowed upon Beleevers. But the Holy Ghoſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly taken is a Perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">That the holy Ghoſt is a Perſon diſtinct fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Father and the Sonne, and proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from them both</note> Again, the Holy Ghoſt is a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon diſtinct from the Father and the Sonne. They are three, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5. 7. The Holy Ghoſt is called <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> to wit, beſides the Father and the Sonne, <hi>John</hi> 14. 16, 17.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the Holy Ghoſt is a Perſon proceeding from the Father &amp; from the Son. This is proved before <hi>pag.</hi> 14 Our care muſt be that we have <hi>the communion of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 13. 14. That <hi>the Holy Ghoſt be ſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in our hearts, Rom.</hi> 5. 5. That <hi>we be filled with the Spirit, Epheſ.</hi> 5. 18. that is, with the ſanctifying graces of the Spirit. <hi>Grow in grace,</hi> 2 Pet. 3. 18.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:169937:42"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church</note> 
               <hi>The Holy Catholike Church</hi>] That is, I beleeve the holy Catholike Church, not in the Holy Catholike Church, as in the Holy Ghoſt; wee muſt beleeve onely in God, that is, truſt onely in him, as before noted, But we muſt beleeve that there is a Holy Catholike Church. And what is that? What is meant by the holy Catholike Church? <note place="margin">What is meant by Church.</note> Firſt, by <hi>Church</hi> here in the Creed, and ſo in the Scripture is not meant that which we commonly call the Church, to wit, the place where the people of God aſſemble and meet together to worſhip God; but the people of God themſelves are meant by the Church. <hi>Great fear came upon all the Church,</hi> Act. 5. 11. <hi>There was a great perſecution againſt the Church, Act.</hi> 8. 1.</p>
            <p>The Church is the company of ſuch as God doth call out of the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169937:43"/> eſtate of ſinne and miſery, into the eſtate of grace and ſalvation. <hi>The Lord added to the Church daily ſuch as ſhould be ſaved, Acts</hi> 2. 47.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Church militant, &amp; the Church triumphant</note> The Church is partly upon earth, and partly in heaven: That part of the Church which is upon earth, is called <hi>The Church militant,</hi> that is, in warfare, warring againſt the world, the fleſh and the Devill. <hi>Fight the good fight of Faith,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 12. It concerns every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church here upon earth. That part of the Church which is in Heaven, is called <hi>the Church tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant,</hi> becauſe it conſiſts of thoſe who have overcome their ſpirituall adverſaries, which here they had to encounter, and now triumph over them. <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith, henceforth is laid up for me the</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:169937:43"/> 
               <hi>Crown of righteouſneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> ſaid the Apoſtle when his departure out of this world was at hand, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Church vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and the Church inviſible.</note> Again, the Church as here upon earth, is either viſible or inviſible. The <hi>viſible Church</hi> conſiſts of all ſuch as are outwardly called, and make an outward profeſſion of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. <hi>Many are called,</hi> (with an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward calling) <hi>but few are choſen, Mat.</hi> 22. 14. So that in the viſible Church are as well wicked as righteous, as well Hypocrites as ſincere Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors. The viſible Church is compared to a Net, wherin are both good fiſhes and bad, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 47, 48, 49. But the <hi>inviſible Church</hi> conſiſts onely of ſuch as are that indeed which they profeſſe themſelves to be, true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, being choſen of God, and called not onely outwardly, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169937:44"/> inwardly and effectually, <hi>called of God according to his purpoſe, Rom.</hi> 8. 28. The Church as it conſiſteth of theſe, is called inviſible, becauſe it appears not unto men, who can onely ſee the outward profeſſion that is made, but the ſincerity of the heart they cannot ſee, that is known onely unto God. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8. 39. And therefore <hi>the Lord</hi> (onely) <hi>knows who are his,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 19.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Church particular, and the Church univerſall or Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</note> Again, the Church is either par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular or univerſall. <hi>A particular Church</hi> is a company of ſuch as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the Goſpell in one particular place. Thus we read of <hi>the Church at Jeruſalem, Acts</hi> 8. 1. <hi>The Church at Antioch, Act.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>the Church at Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Rom.</hi> 16. 1. <hi>the Church at Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>the Church in the houſe of Aquila, and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>illa, Rom.</hi> 16. 3, 5. <hi>The Church in the houſe of Nym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas,</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:169937:44"/> 
               <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 15. <hi>the Church in the houſe of Philemon, Philem. v.</hi> 2. <note place="margin">1 Cor 16. 19. Gal. 1. 2 Rev. 1. 11.</note> Thus there are many particular Churches, <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall Church</hi> is the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Beleevers thorowout the world. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Church which is at Corinth, to them that are ſanctified in Chriſt Ieſus, called to be ſaints,</hi> (there's a particular Church) <hi>with all that in every place call upon the Name of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 2.</note> there's the univerſall Church. So that there's but one uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Church, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> comprehends all particular Churches in it. And this is that which is called <hi>the Catholike Church.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">What the word Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.</note> For <hi>Catholike</hi> is a word de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the Greek, and ſignifies as much as univerſall, or generall. The Epiſtle of <hi>Iames</hi> is called <hi>the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Epiſtle;</hi> ſo both the Epiſtles of <hi>Peter,</hi> and the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>John,</hi> and the Epiſtle of <hi>Jude.</hi> In the Greek it
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169937:45"/> is the word from which is derived this word <hi>Catholike.</hi> Thoſe Epiſtles are called Catholike, or Generall Epiſtles, becauſe they were written to all in generall, and not either to particular perſons, as to <hi>Timothy, Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> &amp;c. or to particular Churches, as to the <hi>Romanes, Corinthians,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How the Church is called holy</note> Now the Church is called <hi>Holy,</hi> Firſt, becauſe all that are outwardly and viſibly of the Church, are called to be holy, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 2. and 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 7. And do profeſſe holineſſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 10. And ſecondly, becauſe all that are indeed of the Church, are holy. They that are of <hi>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Church trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant,</hi> are perfectly holy, they are <hi>made perfect, Hebr.</hi> 12. 23. And they that are of <hi>the Church militant,</hi> are alſo holy in ſome meaſure, though not in full meaſure. <hi>You are waſhed, you are ſanctified,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 6. 11.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169937:45"/> As for ſuch as are altogether unſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, they are rather in the Church, then of the Church, like a wooden Legge, that is outwardly joyned unto the body, but is indeed no part of it. <hi>They went out from us, but they were not of us,</hi> &amp;c. ſaith S. <hi>Iohn</hi> of ſome, <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2. 19</note> who for a while were outwardly joyned to the Church, but afterward fell off, &amp; ſo ſhewed that they were not then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of it, when they were in it. So S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>All are not Iſrael that are of Iſrael, Rom.</hi> 9. 6. that is, all are not the people of God indeed, who are ſuch by outward Profeſſion, and ſo ſeem to be of them. Therefore all muſt take heed of reſting in a bare profeſſion of faith, and be ſure that they have faith indeed, and ſo be joyned unto Chriſt, <hi>Who is the Head of the Body, the Church, Coloſſ.</hi> 1. 18.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169937:46"/> And our union with Chriſt muſt appear by our conformitie unto Chriſt. <hi>He that ſaith he abideth in him, ought himſelfe to walk even as hee walked,</hi> 1 John 2. 6.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints.</note> 
               <hi>The communion of Saints</hi>] By <hi>Saints</hi> are meant holy ones; of ſuch onely doth the Church indeed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, as is before ſhewed. Some think that there are no Saints but in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which is a groſſe conceit; for though all that are in Heaven are Saints, yet all that are Saints are not in Heaven: there are Saints alſo on earth as well as in heaven, although not ſuch compleat and perfect Saints; Heaven being a place that admits of no ſin, whereas <hi>there is not a juſt man upon earth, that doth good, and ſinneth not, Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 20. But holineſſe may be <hi>true holineſſe,</hi> as it is called <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 24. although it
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169937:46"/> be imperfect. <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>the ſaints that are upon the earth,</hi> Pſal. 16. 3. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith that he went <hi>to Jeruſalem to adminiſter to the ſaints, Rom.</hi> 15. 25. And he told the <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians,</hi> that <hi>all the Saints did ſalute them, eſpecially they of</hi> Caeſars <hi>houſhold, Philip.</hi> 4. 22. And indeed the Saints are ſeldome mentioned in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but the Saints on earth are meant. Now that there is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, or (which is all one) a <note n="*" place="margin">The ſame word that is rendred communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 1 Cor. 10. 16. and 2 Cor. 13. 14. is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip Phil. 2. 1. and 1 Ioh. 1. 3.</note> fellowſhip of Saints, we may ſee by that of S. <hi>Iohn, That which we have ſeen and heard declare wee unto you, that ye alſo may have fellowſhip with us; and truely our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 3. Which words alſo ſhew, that the Saints have communion or fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with God, with Chriſt, and with one another.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:169937:47"/>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">The ſaints have communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with God.</note> 1. The Saints have communion with God, hee being peculiarly their God, and they peculiarly his people; he their Father, and they his Children. <hi>Come out from among them, and be ye ſeparate, ſaith the Lord, and touch not the unclean thing, and I will receive you, And will be a Father unto you, and you ſhall be my ſonnes and daughters, ſaith the Lord Almighty,</hi> 2 Cor. 6. 17, 18. The wicked may have an outward formall Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God, by partaking of his Ordinances, but the Saints one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have inward and ſpirituall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him. They <hi>Worſhip God in Spirit, Phil.</hi> 3. 3. Their prayer <hi>goeth not out of fained lips,</hi> Pſal. 17. 1. And as they draw nigh unto God, ſo doth God draw nigh unto them, <hi>Ian</hi> 4. 8. He is nigh unto them in all that they call upon him for, <hi>Deut.</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:169937:47"/> 4. 7. For <hi>he is nigh unto all that call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, even to all that call upon him in truth,</hi> Pſa. 145. 18.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">The Saints have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt</note> 2. The Saints have communion with Chriſt, he being their Head, &amp; they his Members: <hi>Chriſt is the Head of the Church, Ephe.</hi> 5. 23. <hi>We are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his bodie,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 30. They have the communion of his body, and of his blood, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 10. 16. not onely a Sacramentall commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which the wicked may have by receiving the outward Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but a reall, although a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all communion by faith: For <hi>Chriſt doth dwell in their hearts by faith, Epheſ.</hi> 3. 17. By faith they eat the fleſh of Chriſt, and drink his blood, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6. 53, 54. with 57. By Chriſt, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row faith in him, they have acceſſe unto God, and acceptance with God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1, 2. By him they have
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169937:48"/> confidence to make known their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts unto God, and aſſurance to obtain of God whatſoever is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite and needfull for them, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 12. <hi>Iohn</hi> 16. 23. The Saints in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven have more immediate and full communion with God, and with Chriſt, being more immediately and fully joyned unto them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 6, 7. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 23.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">The Saints have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion one with another.</note> 3. The Saints have communion one with another, as having near re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation one to another, being Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of one and the ſame Father, and Members of one and the ſame Bodie; and having near conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one with another, as being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with one and the ſame Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 26. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 27. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 4. and 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 12. 13. The Saints have <hi>the communion of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 13. 14. <hi>the fellowſhip of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:169937:48"/> 
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 1. they muſt needs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have communion and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip one with another.</p>
            <p>As for the Saints in heaven, what communion they have one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, the Scripture ſpeaking ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly, we muſt not be overbold to enquire; onely thus much is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable, that they have ſome communion in that kinde; rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing one in anothers happineſſe, and glorifying God one for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For <hi>Charity never faileth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 8. yea in the Saints in heaven it is made perfect. And <hi>it rejoyceth not in iniquity, but in the truth,</hi> 1 Cor. 13 6. There being ſuch a diſtance betwixt the Saints in heaven, and the Saints on earth, there can be no ſuch communion betwixt them, as they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> pretend, to wit, that the Saints in heaven
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169937:49"/> ſhould pray particularly for the Saints on earth, and procure thoſe good things for them, that they ſtand in need of: and that the ſaints on earth ſhould pray unto the Saints in heaven, and make them Advocates and Mediatours where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to prevaile with God. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that this is moſt injurious (as they practiſe it) unto God, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, we being onely to pray unto God in the name and media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 50. 15. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 9. <hi>Iohn</hi> 16. 23. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, I ſay, the Saints in heaven are not acquainted with the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular eſtate of the Saints on earth, <hi>Iob</hi> 14. 21. And therefore there can be no ſuch communion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, although in reſpect of that which was ſaid before of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, we cannot but conceive, that
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:169937:49"/> the Saints in heaven do in generall think on the Saints on earth, and wiſh them the ſame happineſſe which they have obtained: And ſo the Saints on earth bleſſe God for the Saints in Heaven, thinke and ſpeak honourably of them, and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the vertues that were in them: <hi>Prov.</hi> 10. 7. <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 48. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 12. and 13. 7. As for the Saints on earth, they have communion among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſo as <hi>to conſider one another, and to provoke unto love and good works, Hebr.</hi> 10. 24. <hi>to teach and admoniſh one another, Col.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>to comfort one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 18. <hi>to pray one for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Iames</hi> 5. 15. to ſuccour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve one another, <hi>as every one hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the gift, ſo to miniſter the ſame one to another, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Pet. 4. 10.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">of forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes.</note> 
               <hi>The forgiveneſſe of ſinnes</hi>] This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit is peculiar to the Church;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169937:50"/> The Prophet ſpeaking of Sion, ſaith, <hi>The people that dwell therein ſhall have their ſinnes forgiven, Iſai.</hi> 32. 24. It is a part of the Covenant that God hath made with his people, that he will forgive their iniquity, &amp;c. <hi>Ier.</hi> 31. 33. The Saints themſelves, even the beſt upon earth have need of it. <hi>If thou Lord ſhouldeſt mark iniquities, Lord, who ſhould ſtand? But there is forgiveneſſe with thee, &amp;c Pſal.</hi> 130. 34. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 1, 2.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What ſin is, and the ſeverall kindes of it</note> 
               <hi>Sinne is a tranſgreſſion of the Law,</hi> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 4. It is either originall, or actuall. Originall ſin is that which every one brings with him into the world, <hi>Adam</hi> by his fall loſing that righteouſneſſe in which he was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, and conveyng ſinne and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption into all that by naturall generation proceed from him. <hi>Who can bring a clean thing out of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean?</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:169937:50"/> 
               <hi>not one, Iob</hi> 14. 4. <hi>Behold, I was ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſinne did my mother conceive me,</hi> Pſ. 51. 5. <hi>By one man</hi> (to wit, <hi>Adam</hi>) <hi>ſinne entred into the World,</hi> (that is, into all mankinde) <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12. Actuall ſinne is that which every one makes himſelf guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of in his life and converſation. <hi>All like ſheep have gone aſtray, Iſa.</hi> 53 6. Actuall ſinne is either a ſinne of commiſſion, or of omiſſion: A ſin of commiſſion is, when that which is forbidden, is committed; a ſinne of omiſſion is, when that which is commanded, is omitted. There are many other diſtinctions of ſin, which it were too tedious and not neceſſary to rehearſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of ſinne is, how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in Scripture.</note> Forgiveneſſe of ſinne is a not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting of it. <hi>God was in Chriſtricon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling the world unto himſelf, not impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their treſpaſſes unto them,</hi> 2 Cor.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:169937:51"/> 5. 19. It is called a covering of ſin. <hi>Bleſſed is the man whoſe iniquity is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, and whoſe ſinne is covered,</hi> Pſal. 32. 1. And a blotting out of ſinne. <hi>According to the multitude of thy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercies blot out my tranſgreſſions,</hi> Pſal. 51. 1. Other ſuch like expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons alſo there are, whereby forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes is ſet forth in the Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To forgive ſin belongs only unto God.</note> Onely God can forgive ſinne. As ſinne is committed againſt man, as it is an injury done unto him, ſo he may and ought to forgive it. <hi>Luke</hi> 17. 3, 4. <hi>If thy brother treſpaſſe againſt thee, rebuke him; and if he repent, forgive him. And if be treſpaſſe againſt thee ſeven times in a day, and ſeven times in a day turne again to thee, ſaying, I repent, thou ſhalt forgive him.</hi> Miniſters alſo may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give ſinnes declaratively, ſo as to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:169937:51"/> preach and publiſh forgiveneſſe of ſinnes to ſuch as repent and beleeve. <hi>Whoſe ſoever ſinnes ye remit, they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, &amp;c.</hi> John 20. 23. <hi>Be it known unto you therefore, men and brethren, that through this man</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>is preached unto you forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, Act.</hi> 13. 38. But as ſinne is committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, as it is a tranſgreſſion of his Law, ſo authoritatively onely God can forgive ſinne: <hi>I, even I am he that blotteth out thy tranſgreſſions,</hi> &amp;c <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43. 25. <hi>Who can forgive ſinnes but God onely? Mark</hi> 2. 7. The Scribes that ſpake thoſe words, were right in the doctrine, onely they were wrong in the application of it. Their poſition was good, that onely God can forgive ſinne, but their ſuppoſition was naught, that Chriſt was but a meer man; and ſo their inference was falſe, that Chriſt
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169937:52"/> did blaſpheme in taking upon him ſo to forgive ſinnes as he did.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sinne is forgiven onely through Chriſt.</note> As it is God onely who doth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give ſinne, ſo it is onely Chriſt, both God and man, the Mediatour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and man, for whoſe ſake ſinne is forgiven. Chriſt told his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>That repentance and remiſſion of ſinnes ſhould he preached in his Name, &amp;c. Luke</hi> 24. 42. <hi>Peter</hi> told the Jews, that <hi>him</hi> (to wit, Chriſt) <hi>hath God exalted to be a Prince and a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, for to give repentance to Iſrael, and forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, Act.</hi> 5. 31. <hi>Be it knewn unto you therefore, men and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>that through this man is preached unto you forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, And by him all that beleeve are juſtified from all things, from which you could not be juſtified by the Law of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Acts</hi> 13 38, 39. Chriſt by his Blood hath ſatisfied for our ſinnes, ſo
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:169937:52"/> that thorow him onely we muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect forgiveneſſe of them. <hi>Behold the Lamb of God</hi> (ſaid <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at Chriſt) <hi>which taketh away the ſinnes of the world,</hi> John 1. 29. <hi>He is the propitiation for our ſinnes,</hi> 1 John 2. 2. <hi>Your ſinnes are forgiven you for his Names ſake,</hi> 1 John 2. 12.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What is required of thoſe who would have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of ſinnes.</note> Now if we would have the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of our ſinnes, there is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Repentance. Chriſt ordained <hi>that repentance and remiſſion of ſinnes ſhould be preached in his Name,</hi> Luke. 24. 47. Firſt repentance, and then remiſſion of ſinnes; No remiſſion of ſinnes without repentance. So <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 31. Chriſt is a Saviour <hi>to give re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to Iſrael, and remiſſion of ſins.</hi> When they that were pricked in the heart with <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon, ſaid, <hi>What ſhall we doe to be ſaved? Peter</hi>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:169937:53"/> anſwered, <hi>Repent,</hi> &amp;c. Acts 2. 37. 38. So <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 13. <hi>Repent and be converted, that your ſinnes may be blotted out.</hi> Now repentance imports ſorrow for ſin: <hi>I will acknowledge mine iniquity, I will be ſorry for my ſinne, Pſal.</hi> 38. 18. And forſaking of ſinne: <hi>Let the wicked forſake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts, and turne unto the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him, and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon</hi> Iſai. 55. 7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Faith. <hi>Through this man</hi> (viz. Chriſt) <hi>is preached unto you forgiveneſſe of ſinnes. And by him all that beleeve are juſtified, &amp;c.</hi> Acts 13, 38, 39. This faith, or beleeving, is a laying hold on Chriſt, an adhering unto him, and a relying on him for the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of mercy and forgiveneſſe. <hi>To as many as received him, to them he gave power to be the ſonnes of God, even</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:169937:53"/> 
               <hi>to them that beleeved on his Name,</hi> John 1. 12. There to beleeve in Chriſt, is to receive Chriſt. So Chriſt is ſaid to <hi>dwell in our hearts by faith,</hi> Eph 3. 17.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To forgive others: Thus Chriſt hath taught us to pray unto <hi>God to forgive us our treſpaſſes, as we forgive them that treſpaſſe againſt us, Matth.</hi> 6. 12. And he addes, <hi>For if yee forgive men their treſpaſſes, your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father will alſo forgive you. But if ye forgive not men ther treſpaſſes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will your Father forgive your tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, Matth.</hi> 6. 14, 15. and ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 18 from the 21. Verſe to the end of the Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the body</note> 
               <hi>The reſurrection of the body</hi>] There is a ſpirituall reſurrection, the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing again of the ſoule from the death of ſinne to the life of grace, of which reſurrection ſomething was ſpoken before; but this is not all
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:169937:54"/> the reſurrection that is to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, as (it ſeems) ſome affirmed, ſaying, <hi>that the reſurrection is paſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 18. But there ſhall be alſo a corporall reſurrection, a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing again of the Body; though the ſoul be ſeparated from it, and it be laid in the duſt, and turned to duſt, yet the ſoul ſhall be re-united to it, and it ſhall be raiſed up. This ſeems incredible to a meer naturall man; the Philoſophers at <hi>Athens</hi> marvelled when they heard <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak of it; <hi>Thou ſeemeſt</hi> (ſaid they unto him) <hi>to be a ſetter forth of ſtrange gods; becauſe he preached unto them Ieſus and the reſurrection, Asts</hi> 17. 18. And Verſe 32. <hi>When they heard of the reſurrection of the dead, ſome mocked, &amp; others ſaid, we will hear thee again of this matter.</hi> But they that beleeve Gods Word, beleeve this, that the dead
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:169937:54"/> ſhall riſe again; <hi>I have hope towards God,</hi> (ſaid <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> (meaning the Jews his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries) <hi>alſo allow, that there ſhall be a reſurrection of the dead, both of the juſt, and unjuſt, Acts</hi> 24. 15. <hi>I know that he ſhall riſe again in the reſurrection at the laſt day,</hi> ſaid <hi>Martha</hi> of <hi>Lazarus</hi> being dead, <hi>Iohn</hi> 11. 24. The Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces (a ſect among the Jews) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the reſurrection, as wee read <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 23. and <hi>Acts</hi> 23. 8. But as Chriſt ſaid unto them, <hi>they erred, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God, Matth.</hi> 22. 29. The Power of God ſhewes, that he can raiſe the dead, and the Scriptures ſhew that he will doe it. <hi>Why ſhould it ſeem a t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing incredible unto you, that God ſhould raiſe the dead? Asts</hi> 26. 8. He that could make all things of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, can certainly raiſe up the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:169937:55"/> although it have paſſed thorow never ſo many tranſmutations. And that God will do this, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures clearly teſtifie unto us. See <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 2. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 28, 29. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. the whole Chapter.</p>
            <p>Reaſon alſo grounded upon Scripture doth evince as much. For</p>
            <p n="1">1. The body having been part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with the ſoul either in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe or in ſinne, it is meet that the body ſhould alſo be partner with the ſoul either in the reward, or in the puniſhment. <hi>We muſt all receive the things done in the body, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which we have done, whether it be good or evill,</hi> 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 5. 10. As the things were done in the body, ſo the reward muſt likewiſe be received in the body.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the Saints, their reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is particularly proved by the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:169937:55"/> reſurrection of Chriſt, he being the Head, and they his Members: For as the Head roſe again, ſo muſt the Members; as Chriſt roſe again, ſo muſt they that belong unto Chriſt, and are his. The Scriptures often inferre the reſurrection of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans from Chriſts reſurrection. See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 12, 13, 16, 20, 21, 22, 23. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 14. and 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 14.</p>
            <p>What a change there ſhall be of the body at the reſurrection, Chriſt ſhews, ſaying, <hi>In the reſurrection they neither marry, nor are given in marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, but are as the Angels of God in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Mat.</hi> 22. 30. And the Apoſtle ſets it forth more at large, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 15. 42, 43, 44. where, ſpeaking of the body, and ſhewing how much it ſhall differ in the reſurrection from what now it is, he ſaith, <hi>It is ſown in corruption, it is raiſed in incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</hi>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:169937:56"/> 
               <hi>It is ſown in diſhonour, it is raiſed in glory; It is ſown in weakneſſe, it is raiſed in power. It is ſown a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall body, it is raiſed a ſpirituall body.</hi> Such as are found alive at Chriſts comming, and ſhall not die, and therefore not properly riſe againe, ſhall yet have this change, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle there ſheweth, <hi>verſe</hi> 51, 52, 53. But this bleſſed and glorious change of the body, belongs onely to the godly; as for the wicked, they ſhall indeed riſe again, and be changed, but their reſurrection ſhall be unto condemnation, <hi>John</hi> 5. 29. And their change ſhall be to perpetuall ſhame and contempt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 2. Onely they that are the living members of Chriſt, and <hi>have their converſation in Heaven,</hi> can expect that <hi>Chriſt will change their vile bodies, and make them like unto his moſt glorious body,</hi> as the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:169937:56"/> Apoſtle teacheth, <hi>Philip.</hi> 3. 20, 21.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of life everlaſting</note> 
               <hi>And life everlaſting</hi>] This is <hi>the end of our faith,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 9. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fitly put in the end of the <hi>Creed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That after this life, which is but temporall, there ſhall be another life which is eternall, the Scripture is plain and expreſſe, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 2. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 16. and in many other places.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun here.</note> Everlaſting life is begun here, and ſo it is called the life of grace. <hi>He that beleeveth on the Son, hath ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life,</hi> John 3. 36. He ſaith not, <hi>ſhall have,</hi> but <hi>hath.</hi> So <hi>John</hi> 5. 24. <hi>Verily, verily I ſay unto you, he that hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth my word, and beleeveth on him that ſent me, hath everlaſting life.</hi> So 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 14. <hi>We know that we are paſſed from death to life, becauſe we love the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> He means from the death of ſinne to the life of grace; and that this life of grace is a beginning of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:169937:57"/> eternall life, he ſhews in the Verſe following, <hi>Whoſoever hateth his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is a Murtherer, and no murtherer hath eternall life abiding in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life perfected hereafter.</note> Everlaſting life is perfected here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, and ſo its called the life of glory. <hi>In the world to come everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life, Mark</hi> 10. 30. to wit, in the fulneſſe and perfection of it. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the ſoul this life is perfected immediately after its ſeparation from the the bodie, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 23. In reſpect of the bodie it is perfected at the reſurrection, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 52, 53, 54. and 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 16, 17.</p>
            <p>What a life this life of glory is, onely they fully know who do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it: It is <hi>a glory that ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, Rom.</hi> 8. 18. <hi>It doth not yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear what we ſhall be,</hi> I <hi>John</hi> 3. 2. But thus much by the Scripture we may know, that it conſiſts in a clear viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:169937:57"/> of God, and a full fruition of him. See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 12. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 6, 7, 8. and 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 3.</p>
            <p>Such is the happineſſe of this life, that it is free from all evill, and full of all good. 1. It is free from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, both all evill of ſinne, and alſo all evill of affliction. Whiles we are here in this mortall bodie, all wee can do is to keep ſinne under, that it do not reigne in us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 12. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. 8. But in the life to come ſinne ſhall not ſo much as be in us. They that enjoy that life, are <hi>juſt men made perfect, Heb</hi> 12. 23. Here <hi>man is born to trouble, even as the ſparks flie upward,</hi> Job 5. 7. But in the life to come, there ſhall be a perfect free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from all moleſtation, <hi>All tears ſhall be wiped away,</hi> Revel. 7. 17.</p>
            <p>2. It is full of all good. For in that life God is enjoyed, and that
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:169937:58"/> moſt fully and perfectly; and ſo far forth as any enjoy God, they are ſure to enjoy all good. <hi>Delight thy ſelf in the Lord, and he ſhall give thee the deſires of thine heart,</hi> Pſal. 37. 4. <hi>Whom have</hi> I <hi>in heaven but thee? and there is none upon earth that</hi> I <hi>deſire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thee,</hi> Pſal. 73. 25. <hi>As for me</hi> I <hi>will behold thy face in righteouſneſſe;</hi> I <hi>ſhdll be ſatisfied when</hi> I <hi>awake with thy likeneſſe,</hi> Pſal. 17. 15. <hi>Thou wilt ſhew me the path of life; in thy preſence is fulneſſe of joy, at thy right hand there are pleaſures for ever more,</hi> Pſalm. 16. 11. What is this life in compariſon of that which is to come? yet while this life laſteth, that life which is to come muſt be acquired. For <hi>after death commeth judgement,</hi> Heb. 9. 27. <hi>As a man ſoweth</hi> (here,) <hi>ſo ſhall he reap</hi> (hereafter,) <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 7. Therefore <hi>fight the good fight of faith, and lay hold</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:169937:58"/> 
               <hi>on eternall life,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 12. Sow to the Spirit, that ſo you may of the Spirit reap life everlaſting, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 8.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What the word A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men doth ſignifie, and how it is uſed.</note> 
               <hi>Amen.</hi>] This word <hi>Amen</hi> is an Hebrew word, but moſt common in all languages. It ſignifies as much as truth. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 65. 16. <hi>The God of truth;</hi> the word in the Originall there ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>truth,</hi> is <hi>Amen.</hi> So <hi>Revel.</hi> 3. 14. Chriſt is ſtiled <hi>the Amen,</hi> that is, <hi>the Truth,</hi> as he ſtiles himſelf, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14. 6. And ſo in that place of the <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> it follows immediately, <hi>The faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and true Witneſſe;</hi> by which words is declared what is meant by <hi>the Amen.</hi> Sometimes the word <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> is uſed adverbially, and imports as much as <hi>verily</hi> or <hi>truly. I tell you of a truth, there be ſome ſtanding here, which ſhall not taſte of death, till they ſee the Kingdome of God,</hi> Luke 9. 27. In Mat. 16. 28. it is, <hi>Verily I ſay unto you,</hi>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:169937:59"/> 
               <hi>there be ſome ſtanding here, &amp;c.</hi> In the Originall the word there rendred <hi>Verily,</hi> is <hi>Amen,</hi> and ſo it is rendred alſo in other places. Sometimes this word <hi>Amen</hi> is uſed only by way of wiſhing, to expreſſe a deſire that a thing migbt be, though there bee no perſwaſion that it ſhall be. When the falſe Prophet had ſaid, that God would ſhortly bring backe the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and the things that were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed into Babylon, <hi>Ieremiah</hi> ſaid, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Ier.</hi> 28. 6. Not that he aſſented to what the other ſaid, but onely he wiſhed that it might be. But for moſt part the word <hi>Amen</hi> is uſed for confirmation of that which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and to ſhew the truth and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the thing as alſo ones aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto it, and aſſurance of it. And ſometimes it is uſed in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a ſentence; thus our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:169937:59"/> often uſed it; <hi>Amen,</hi> or doubling the word, <hi>Amen, Amen, Iſay, &amp;c.</hi> Joh. 3. 3, 5. where our Tranſlators ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it <hi>Verily, verily.</hi> Sometimes it is uſed in the end of a ſentence, or of many ſentences; as <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 5. <hi>Who is God bleſſed for ever, Amen.</hi> And <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 26. <hi>To him be glory for ever. Amen.</hi> So in the end of the Lords Prayer, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 13. And in the end of the Goſpell written by S. <hi>Matthew,</hi> S. <hi>Mark,</hi> S. <hi>Luke,</hi> and S. <hi>John.</hi> So alſo in the end of all <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, of both <hi>Peters,</hi> of the firſt and ſecond of <hi>John,</hi> of <hi>Jude,</hi> &amp; of the <hi>Revelation.</hi> The word therefore <hi>(Amen)</hi> doth teach us to be fully perſwaded and aſſured of the truth of the Articles before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed. <hi>Let us draw near with a true heart in a full aſſurance of faith, Heb.</hi> 10. 22. <hi>Stand faſt in the faith,</hi> 1 Cor. 16. 13. <hi>Let us hold faſt the profeſſion of our faith without wavering,</hi> Heb. 10. 23.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:169937:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169937:60"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
